A Guide to the Robert Taylor Preston Papers, 1849-1871 (Bulk 1861-1862)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- June 16-22, 1861 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Special Order No. 13: Strict orders will be given to the general guard to prevent the sale of ardent spirits in camp. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Directions for transfers. Signed: Thomas Rhett, June 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 9: The Colonel commanding regrets that it has been found necessary to reiterate General Order No. 16 of Head Quarters, Dept. of Alexandria. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. To: Col. Preston. Transfers to be places into effect tomorrow. Signed: Thomas Rhett, June 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Dept. of Alexandria, Camp at Manassas Junction. General Order No. 19: Transfer and Dispositions of Companies. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 18, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. Detail for tomorrow. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 19, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac, Manassas Junction. General Order No. 20: Organization of the First Corps. of Army of the Potomac. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 21, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade. Marching Instructions with respect to Special Order No. 20: By Order of Phillip Cocke, June 21, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Pickens. General Order No. 1: General Order No. 19 of Head Quarters, Dept. of Alexandria will be carried into effect today. By order of Col. Terrett, Signed: Thomas J. Rhett, June 21, 1861
- June 23-30, 1861 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of Potomac. Manassas Junction. General Order No. 25: Ordered changes in leave application process. By order of Col. Cocke, June 23, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advanced Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax Co. Ho. Special Order No. 18: Report forthwith to the Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac Requisitions for ammunition needs for service in the face of the Enemy. By order of Genl. Bonham, June 23, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade To: Col. Preston. Make requisitions for ammunition. By order of Col. Cocke, June 24, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters of the VA. Forces, Richmond. Personal Order No. 29: Information regarding the first periodical muster for payment of the Virginia Volunteers. By order of General Lee, Signed: Col. Cocke, June 24, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke, Head Quarters The 28th Regiment, 5th Brigade will report forthwith for supplies. By order of Col. Preston, June 24, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke. Regimental Order: It is Important that the regiment be at all times held in readiness for movement. Signed: Col. Preston, June 25, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade. In order to carry out Order No. 17, we are imposing limits on personal baggage herein defined. By order of Col. Cocke. Also enclosed, on same paper: General Order No. 17: All officers of the Quarter Master's department, Prepare to advance at short notice. All troops will be furnished with ten days rations and forty rounds of ammunition. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 25, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac. Special Order: B.F. Terry, T.S. Tubbock and D. Conner of the Texas Rangers are acting as scouts. Supply them due provisions. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 25, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac. All feasible measures should be taken to secure an efficient equipment and outfit in all respects. Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 25, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke, Regimental Order: Reading of Rules and Articles for the government of the Army of Virginia. Signed: Col. Preston, June 25, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade. To: Col. Preston. Concerning the movement of surplus baggage to be stored at Orange. Signed: John B. Cocke, June 26, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke, Army of the Potomac. To: Col. Cocke. Request for instructions for loading picket and camp guard. Signed: Col. Preston, June 26, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke, Army of the Potomac. Regimental Order: Reduce our baggage to within limits stated. Signed: Col. Preston, June 27, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac. General Order: Surgeon Thomas H. Williams appointed Medical Director of the Army of the Potomac. By order of Brig. General Beauregard, Signed: Thomas Jordan, June 27, 1861
  - From Camp Cocke, Army of the Potomac. Regimental Order: John A. Cobb transfer to Hospital duty. Signed: Col. Preston, June 27, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade. General Order: Order of documentation of the sick of the Company by the surgeon and report to company commander. Signed: Col. Cocke, June 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advanced Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. Order: Every commander is to procure a Confederate Flag. By order of Brig. Genl. Bonham, Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. General Order No. 7 The parole and countersign will go into effect at twilight and continue for twenty-four hours. Also, instructions for dealing with approaching parties and security. By order of Brig. Genl. Bonham, Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 28, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 5th Brigade. General Order: Carry into effect Order No. 29 from Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac regarding mustering. Signed: Phillip Cocke, June 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. Regimental Quarter Master will not suffer the animals to be used for private purposes. Leaves of absence will not be granted to Teamsters. By order of Brig. Genl. Bonham, Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. Regarding Guard Duty, sentinels must challenge so as to be heard distinctly two or three times repeatedly before cocking their weapon. By order of Brig. Genl. Bonham, Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Army of the Potomac, Manassas Junction. General Order No. 29: Concerning the mustering of troops tomorrow. By order of Genl. Beauregard Signed: Sam. Jones, June 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. Monthly Returns tomorrow. By order of Brig. Genl. Bonham, Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 29, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. Order to remove obstructions of turnpikes at Centreville and Old Braddock Road. Signed: Geo. N. Lay, June 30, 1861
  - From: Camp Cocke, Army of the Potomac. Request for supply report. Signed: Col. Preston, June 30, 1861
- July-December 1861 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Army of the Potomac, Fairfax C.H. To: Col. Preston. Call on the Brig. General tomorrow after breakfast. Signed: Geo. Lay, July 1, 1861
  - Requisition for Ordnance and Ordnance Stores for the use of the 28th Regiment of the Va. Volunteers. Signed: P. Breckenridge, September 20. 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Falls Church. To: Col. Preston. Report to Genl. Longstreet immediately upon your arrival, September 25, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces, Camp at Masons Hill, Regarding troop movement. By order of Col. Preston, September 26, 1861
  - From: Masons Hill. Col. Preston's response to criticism of misinterpreted orders. Signed: Col. Preston, September 26, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Advances Forces. To: Col. Preston. Request for troop movement, September 27, 1861
  - From: Fairfax Co. Virginia. To: Col. Preston. Inquiry on the probable state of Masons Hill. Signed: M. Mason, September 28, 1861
  - From: Richmond. To: Col. Preston. Regarding Transfers, October 3, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters 28th Regiment Va. Volunteers, Camp near Centreville. The regiment under my command is the one selected form the 5th Brigade to report to construct a portion of the Advanced Guard. Signed: Col. Preston, October 17, 1861
  - From: Warrington Va. To: Col. Preston. Inquiry into the state of Mason's Hill. Signed: M. Mason, November 4, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, Centreville. To Col. Preston. Presentation of State colors by Governor. Signed: J. E. Johnston, November 4, 1861
  - From: Head Quarters, 28th Regiment Va. Volunteers. Special Requisition. Signed: Col. Preston, Novembeer 9, 1861
  - From: Near Centreville. Certificate granting Col. Preston a medical leave of absence. Signed: Saml. A. McConkey, November 23, 1861
  - From: Camp Pickens To Col. Preston. Personnel transfer. Signed: H. Wells, November 24, 1861
  - From; Camp, 28th Regiment Va. Volunteers, near Centreville. Col. Preston wished and is recommended an extension of leave for 30 days. Signed: Saml. A. McConkey, December 19, 1861
  - From; Head Quarters, 28th Regiment Va. Volunteers, Centreville. To: Col. Preston. State of the 28th Va. Vol. Signed: Henry Johnston, December 26 ,1861
- January-March 1862 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - From: Winchester. News of the death of James Frances Preston. Signed: J. F. Kent, February 5, 1862
  - From: Mount Joy. Request for continued leave of absence. Signed: Wm. T. Patton, February 22, 1862
  - From: Bedford Va. Personal Orders. Signed: A. S. Minter, March 1, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, Centreville. General Order No. 7: A board of medical officers will assemble to examine applicants for discharge, March 3, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, 28th Regiment of the VA. Volunteers. Personnel Report. Signed: Col. Preston, March 4, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, 28th Regiment of the VA. Volunteers. Announcement of upcoming squad drill. Signed: Col. Preston, March 4, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, 2nd Division, Army of the Potomac. Orders for the movement of baggage to the rear by way of railroad, March 5, 1862
  - Medical leave certificate. Signed: O. W. Hearn, March 7, 1862
  - From: Lauderdale. To: Col. Preston. Concerning medical leave. Signed: J. A. Johnston, March 10, 1862
  - To: Col. Preston. Regarding the destruction of whiskey distilleries and employing Negro men in the Army. Signed: F. E. Willis, March 18, 1862
  - List of absence of Co. B 28th Regiment of the VA. Volunteers, March 19, 1862
  - To: Col. R. T. Preston. Regarding sickness and failure to report. Signed: J. A. Johnston, March 21, 1862
  - To: Col. R. T. Preston. Signed: William Watts, January 23, 1862
  - To: Col. R. T. Preston. Signed: William Watts, February 19, 1862
  - To: Col. R. T. Preston. Signed: W. B. Preston, March 4, 1862
  - To: Col. R. T. Preston. Signed W. B. Preston
- April-May 1862 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - rom: Head Quarters, 28th Regiment of the VA. Volunteers. All officers are ordered to arrest any soldier guilty of firing his musket against orders. Signed: Col. Preston, April 22, 1862
  - From: Richmond To: Col. Preston. Signed: Charles B. Ball, April 29, 1862
  - To: Col. Preston. Regarding Extension of sick leave, April 28, 1862
  - News clipping: A letter from the Confederate states of America War Department. Official letter relative to the conscription act. Sign Geo. W. Randolph, Secretary of War, April 30, 1862
    Clipping (gif)
  - From: Lynchburg To: Col. Preston. Regarding need of money. Signed: F. B. Deanefor, April 30, 1862
  - From: Executive Department To: Col. Preston. Authorization for Col. Preston to form a Volunteer regiment. Signed: John Lechen, May 3, 1862
  - From Richmond. Information Regarding the formation of a regiment as a guerrilla band and reports on Norfolk, Williamsburg and Harrisonburg. Signed: W. Younger, May 6, 1862
  - To: John S. Peck. Intercept the Yankees at Pearisburg. Signed: Wilson Lively, May 8, 1862
  - From Union. To: Col. Preston. Regarding movement of cattle to Blacksburg. Advise women and children to stay at home. Information on the position of the Yankees at Lunenburg. Signed: A. T. Caperton, May 15, 1862
  - Telegraph of the Southern Telegraph Companies, Recorded at Christiansburg from Lynchburg: To: Col. Preston. Guns can be transferred from the Hospital provided orders are given from Richmond. Signed: F. B. Deane Jr., May 15, 1862
    Telegraph (gif)
  - From: Head Quarters 2nd Division. Testimony to Col. Preston's Honorable character as a soldier. In response to his request to rejoin the Army. Signed: James Longstreet, May 19, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, 3rd Brigade 2nd Corps, Camp near Laurel Church, Henrico Co. VA. Report that Col. Preston was not re-elected for duty. Signed: G. E. Pickett, May 19, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, 3rd Brigade. Condolences to Col. Preston for not being reinstated in a position of service. Signed: George S. Pickett, May 19, 1862
  - Order No. 28: Act to organize bands of Rangers. Signed: A. L. Long, May 26, 1862
  - From: Dublin Depot. Authorization for Col. Preston to Raise a Regiment of Rangers. Signed: Lyle Alanke, May 27, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters. To: Secretary of War. Request that Col. Preston be returned to service. Signed: J. A. Johnston, May 28, 1862
  - From: Cave Spring Va. To: Col. Preston. Request for transfer to Col. Preston's Regiment. Signed: H. Stevens, May 28, 1862
- June-December 1862 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - From: Adjutant General's Office, Richmond, Va. Regarding General Order No. 1 of Major General John B. Floyd. Signed: Wm. H. Richardson, A.G., June 4, 1862
  - From: Wytheville. Col. R.T. Preston and Col. James P. Hammet are authorized to raise a regiment of Volunteers for service. Signed: John B. Floyd, June 10, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters, Virginia State Line, Wytheville. Col. Preston and Col. Hammet are authorized to raise and organize men from the Counties of Montgomery, Roanoke, Botetourt, Craig, Monroe and Giles. Signed: John B. Floyd, June 11, 1862
  - From: Bedford, Va. To: Col. Preston Regarding raising of a regiment for the State. Signed: P. Huddleston, June 13, 1862
  - From: Richmond. Information regarding troops on the Chickahominy river (Mc Clellen and Lee), Battle of May 31, and the physical condition of General Johnston. Signed: B. R. Johnston., June 13, 1862
  - From: Adjutant General's Office of Virginia, Richmond. To: Col. Preston. Authorization to raise a regiment of infantry. Signed: Wm, H. Richardson, June 17, 1862
  - From: Lynchburg. To: Col. Preston. Regarding change of employment. Signed: F. B. Deanefor, June 19, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters Va. State Line, Wytheville. Special Order: Col. Preston is authorized to grant transportation of troops to Wytheville for service in the State Line. Signed: William E. Peters, June 29, 1862
  - From: Adjutant General's Office. Call for the formation of Militias to unite in effort to repel the Enemy. Signed: Wm. H. Richardson, Adjt. Genl. of Va., August 4, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters Va. State Line, Wytheville, Va. To: Col. Preston. Regarding the militia service. Signed: John B. Floyd, August 4, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters Va. State Line, Wytheville, Va. To; Col. Preston. Bring everyone foreword to the depot at Wytheville. Signed: John B. Floyd, August 11, 1862
  - From: Head Quarters Va. State Line, Wytheville, Va. General Order No. 5: Regarding the organization of militias to serve the Virginia State Line. Signed: Major General John B. Floyd, August 19, 1862
  - From: Commonwealth of Virginia. To: Col. Preston. Commission to Colonel of Infantry. Signed: John Letches, August 23, 1862
  - From: The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company, Christiansburg Depot. Freight receipt. Signed: by Depot agent, November 1, 1862
  - From: Salem Va. Statement of goods received from Christiansburg Depot. Signed: James Wade, November 17, 1862
  - From: Salem Va. To: Col. Preston. Statement of wheat received. Signed: James Wade, December 12, 1862
  - From: Blacksburg Va. To: Col. Preston. Proposal for coal mining venture at "Machine Hill." Signed: W. G. Atkinson, December 27, 1862
  - From: Richmond. To: Col. Preston. Request for a certificate of estimated loss. Signed: M. Mason, December 30, 1862
- 1863 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - From: Solitude. Call to ask all the men of Montgomery and Roanoke to help repel the enemy. Signed: Col. Robert Preston, May 13, 1863
  - To: Col. Preston. Regarding the formation of a committee to assist in the raising of companies to fight. Signed: J. H. Anderson, September 9, 1862
  - From: The Virginia and Tennessee Railroad Company, Christiansburg Depot. Freight receipt for goods sent to Salem. Received of Col. Preston, November 8, 1863
- 1866, 1871 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Certified document of the United States of America, Department of State. Acknowledgment of the President's Warrant of Pardon. Signed: Robert T. Preston, January 8, 1866
  - From: Solitude, Montgomery Co. Va. Information regarding the depositions on the case of Thos. L. Preston v/s W. A. Stuart. Signed: Robert T. Preston, November 8, 1871
- Undated manuscript materials. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - From: Richmond. Certificate of Examination of Lieut. Col. Samuel B. Paul. Signed: Medical Director of the 2nd Division, Army of the Potomac, February 5
  - From Dublin. To: Col. Preston. Report that no arms were received. Signed: James Wade, May 13
  - From: Head Quarters, Camp Smith. Orders regarding Col. Preston Assuming command of all infantry Companies of the Volunteer Forces of Virginia. Signed: Col. Preston, May 17
  - From: Richmond, War Department Confederate States. Regarding letter of the 14th accepting volunteer regiments. Signed: Secretary of War, May 19
  - From Lynchburg. To. Col. Preston. Detail a committee to value the horses in the company warehouse, May 20
  - From Lynchburg To: Col. Preston. Resignation of position. Signed: W. Watts, June 1
  - From: 8th Brigade. Concerning mess accounts, November 2
  - From: Adjutant General's Office of Virginia, Richmond. An uncompleted form letter regarding the Raising of a Volunteer Regiment.
  - Stamped, canceled envelope addressed to Col. R. Preston, Near Christiansburg, Montgomery Co. Virginia. n.d. Requisition for ordnance and ordnance stores for the use of the 28th regiment of the Virginia Volunteers.
  - Orders and correspondence between General Longstreet and Col. Preston at Mason's Hill.
  - From: Col. Preston. Marching orders.
  - Morning Report form.
  - Order No. 9: Prepare and hold in readiness to march to Lynchburg Sunday morning the 26th. By order of Col. Preston.
  - Regarding subsistence to officers.
  - Designation of company commanders. Signed: Col. Preston.
  - Request to assume former position at Mason's Hill. Signed: Col. Preston.
  - Order of punishment of James W. Johnson for leaving camp and being drunk. Signed: Col. Preston.
  - To: Col. Preston. Request for transfer.
- Pardon signed by President Andrew Johnson granting Preston a "full pardon and amnesty for all offenses by him committed, arising from participation, direct or implied, in the said rebellion...," September 10, 1865 (Oversize 1)